Guide to the Jeremiah Mason Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jeremiah Mason papers
1798-1844
MS 347
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
Correspondence during his terms as Attorney General of New Hampshire (1802-1805), as a senator in the United States Senate (1813-1817), and as a representative in the New Hampshire House of Representatives (1820-1824). The correspondence also reflects his activities in private practice and in local issues, such as the Dartmouth College Case (1818-1819). The correspondence, which is largely political, reflects the issues of the times, among them Aaron Burr's activities, the Tripolitan War, the War of 1812, the presidential elections of 1816 and 1824, the embargo and the tariff. Among the correspondents are Nicholas Biddle, David Daggett, Rufus King, William Plumer, Benjamin Tappan and Bennett Tyler.
Mason, Jeremiah, 1768-1848
Existence and Location of Copies
Additional information not yet available in the online version of the finding aid exists in the repository. Contact Manuscripts and Archives for assistance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Jeremiah Mason Papers span the years 1798-1844. The collection, although small, is an exceedingly rich one for the early years of the nineteenth century.
Family and personal matters are touched upon in the correspondence, but the bulk of the material is concerned with the political scene between 1800 and 1825. Mason's correspondence with people both in and outside of Washington kept him informed of the political climate during the administrations of Thomas Jefferson, James Madison, and James Monroe. Of particular interest are the letters of Nicholas Biddle, President fo the Bank of the United States.
Among the topical subjects mentioned in the papers are Aaron Burr's activities, various bills before the House and Senate, the Tripolitan War, treaties, consummated or otherwise, with Great Britain and Spain, the War of 1812, the presidential elections of 1816 and 1824, the embargo, the tariff, and the Dartmouth College Case.
The Jeremiah Mason Papers were purchased in 1964.
Biographical / Historical
1782-84: Prepared for college under Nathan Tisdale of Lebanon
1784: Entered Yale College, New Haven.
1788: Graduated from Yale College.
1788-89: Read law in the office of the Hon. Simeon Baldwin in New Haven.
1789-91: Read law in the office of Gen. Stephen Row Bradley in Wetminster, VT.
1791: Admitted to the Vermont bar.
1791-94: Practiced law in Westmoreland, New Hampshire
1794-97: Practiced law in Walpole, New Hampshire
1797: Removed to Portsmouth, New Hampshire (1797-1832).
1799: Married Mary Means, 1777-1858, daughter of Colonel Robert Means of Amherst, New Hampshire.
1802: Appointed Attorney General of New Hampshire (served 1802-05)
1813: Elected as a Federalist to the United States Senate (served 1813-17)
1815: Received an honory L.L.D. From Bowdoin College.
1816: Declined appoint as Chief Justice of New Hampshire.
1817: Resigned from the Senate; re-entered private practice; received an honorary L.L.D. From Harvard College.
1818-19: Associated with Daniel Webster and Jeremiah Smith in the Dartmouth College Case.
1820: Elected tot he New Hampshire House of Representatives (served 1820-24)
1823: Received an honorary L.L.D. from Dartmouth College.
1824: Candidate for election to the United States Senate; defeated in legislature by one vote.
1828: Chosen president and counsel for Portsmouth Branch of the Bank of the United States (served 1828-32).
1832: Moved to Boston to practice law.
1838: Retired from the active practice of law.
1848 Oct 14: Died in Boston; buried in Mt. Auburn Cemetery, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
Elections -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- History -- Tripolitan War, 1801-1805; United States -- History -- War of 1812; United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century; United States -- Politics and government; Lawyers; Politicians; Austin, James Trecothick, 1784-1870; Biddle, Nicholas, 1786-1844; Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836; Chauncey, Charles, 1777-1849; Daggett, David, 1764-1851; Evans, Estwick, 1787-1866; Havens, Nathaniel Appleton, 1762-1831; King, Rufus, 1755-1827; Lawrence, Amos, 1786-1852; Loring, Charles G. (Charles Greely), 1794-1867; Marsh, Charles, 1765-1849; Mason, Jeremiah, 1768-1848; Parrott, John Fabyan, 1767-1836; Plumer, William, 1759-1850; Sharp, Daniel, 1783-1853; Smith, Jeremiah, 1759-1842; Tappan, Benjamin, 1773-1857; Thompson, Thomas W., 1766-1821; Tudor, William, 1779-1830; Tyler, Bennet, 1783-1858; Williams, John, 1778-1837; Dartmouth College -- History
- Correspondence
  - 1798-1807 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1814-1815 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1816-1817 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1818-1820 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1822-1823 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1824 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1826-1827 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1828 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1829 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1832-1844 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Typewritten extract from the autobiography of Jeremiah Mason (Box 1, Folder 11)